<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
$Id$
vim: softtabstop=2 shiftwidth=2
-->

<!-- =========================================================================
Usage Guide
-->
<chapter id="usage"><title>Usage Guide</title>
  <para>The usage of log4sh is simple. There are only a few simple steps required to setup and use log4sh in your application.</para>

  <para>
    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem><para>preconfigure log4sh (properties file)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>source the log4sh script code into the shell script</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>configure log4sh in code (optional)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>call logging statements</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>

  <section id="usage-preconfigure"><title>Preconfigure log4sh (optional)</title>
    <para>To preconfigure log4sh, create a properties file (see the <link linkend="properties_file" endterm="properties_file.title" /> later in this document).  If the properties file is not located in the same directory as log4sh, set the <varname>LOG4SH_CONFIGURATION</varname> environment variable to the full path to the properties file.  If you do not wish to preconfigure log4sh, please read the <link linkend="usage-code" endterm="usage-code.title" /> section later in this chapter.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="usage-source"><title>Source log4sh</title>
    <para>To source the code into your script (also known as including), one uses the sourcing ability of shell to source one script into another.  See the following quick example for how easy this is done.</para>

    <example id="ex:sourcing_log4sh">
      <title>Sourcing external shell code into current program</title>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
#! /bin/sh

# source log4sh from current directory
. ./log4sh
]]></programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Here is some sample code that looks for log4sh in the same directory as the script is located, as well as the current directory. If log4sh could not be found, it exits with an error. If log4sh is found, it is loaded, along with the <filename>log4sh.properties</filename> file in the current directory (see the following example). It then logs a message at the &info; level to <filename>STDOUT</filename>.</para>

    <example id="ex:hello_world_via_properties_file">
      <title>Hello, world (using properties file)</title>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
#! /bin/sh
#
# log4sh example: Hello, world
#
myDir=`dirname $0`

# find and source log4sh
if [ -r "$myDir/log4sh" ]; then
  log4shDir=$myDir
elif [ -r "./log4sh" ]; then
  log4shDir=.
else
  echo "fatal: could not find log4sh" >&2
  exit 1
fi
. $log4shDir/log4sh

# say Hello to the world
logger_info "Hello, world"
]]></programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Here is the <filename>log4sh.properties</filename> file for the previous example. Save it in the same directory you are running the above script from.</para>

    <example id="ex:hello_world_properties_file">
      <title>Hello, world; properties file</title>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
#
# log4sh example: Hello, world properties file
#

# Set root logger level to INFO and its only appender to A1
log4sh.rootLogger=INFO, A1

# A1 is set to be a ConsoleAppender.
log4sh.appender.A1=ConsoleAppender

# A1 uses a PatternLayout.
log4sh.appender.A1.layout=PatternLayout
log4sh.appender.A1.layout.ConversionPattern=%-4r [%t] %-5p %c %x - %m%n
]]></programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section id="usage-code"><title id="usage-code.title">Configure log4sh in code</title>
    <para>If log4sh was not preconfigured, the default configuration will be equivalent the config shown below.</para>
 
    <para>Note: log4sh will complain if no configuration file was specified or found. If you meant for the default configuration to be used, or you want to configure log4sh via code, make sure to define the <varname>LOG4SH_CONFIGURATION</varname> with the value of '<constant>none</constant>'.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
log4sh.rootLogger=ERROR, stdout
log4sh.appender.stdout=ConsoleAppender
log4sh.appender.stdout.layout=PatternLayout
log4sh.appender.stdout.layout.ConversionPattern=%-4r [%t] %-5p %c %x - %m%n
]]></programlisting>

    <para>To configure log4sh in code, simply call the appropriate functions in your code. The following code sample loads log4sh from the current directory, configures it for <filename>STDERR</filename> output, and the logs a message at the &info; level.</para>

    <example id="ex:hello_world_code">
      <title>Hello, world (configured in code)</title>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
#! /bin/sh
#
# log4sh example: Hello, world
#

# load log4sh (disabling properties file warning) and clear the default
# configuration
LOG4SH_CONFIGURATION='none' . ./log4sh
log4sh_resetConfiguration

# set the global logging level to INFO
logger_setLevel INFO

# add and configure a FileAppender that outputs to STDERR, and activate the
# configuration
logger_addAppender stderr
appender_setType stderr FileAppender
appender_file_setFile stderr STDERR
appender_activateOptions stderr

# say Hello to the world
logger_info 'Hello, world'
]]></programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section id="usage-logging"><title>Logging with log4sh</title>
    <para>Once log4sh is loaded, logging is as simple as calling the appropriate logging function with a message to be logged. Take a look at the above examples to see just how easy it was to log the statement <literal>"Hello, world"</literal> at an &info; level.</para>

    <para>The samples above show the standard way of logging a message via log4sh. That standard method is by calling the appropriate function, and passing the message as a parameter.</para>

    <example id="ex:logger_info">
      <title>Standard method of logging a message</title>
      <programlisting>logger_info 'message to log'</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>There is a second way of logging as well. The second method is via pipes. What this method is really good for is logging the standard output (<filename>STDOUT</filename>) of a command to the logfile. Piping <command>echo</command> statements is a bit silly, but something like piping the output of a <command>ls</command> is more practical (e.g. <literal>ls -l |logger_info</literal>).</para>

    <example><title>Alternate method of logging a message</title>
      <programlisting>echo 'message to log' |logger_info</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

</chapter>
